גוט טוב, Gut tov, today’s דף daf is דף קוף, daf kuf,
100, the odometer has turned, okay, so we are now into triple
digits,
and okay, and now we’ll pick up again from לימא להו, lema
lehu, two lines from the
top. Basically the case is that a person has a field here,
there was a major thoroughfare going through his field, he basically said,
I want to take back
this road for myself, and I’m going to give them a different
road which is more convenient for me, and the משנה mishna says
that
they get the road he gave them but they also get the
road that they always had. So he basically, he loses both ways,
sort of like תמורה, tmura, you’re trying to exchange one animal for
another and the first one stays קדוש kadosh and the second one
becomes קדוש kadosh too. It is like that, it just occurred to
me. Anyway, so the question is why? Like make up your mind,
either it was a good swap or not a good swap, but
one way or the other, the רבים rabbim should not have both
roads. So the גמרא gemara said it wasn’t a good swap fundamentally
because you are doing it unilaterally, nobody represented the רבים, rabbim, and
since you’re doing it unilaterally, we’re afraid that any road you give
them will be, you know, will be not as convenient, will be
out of the way, won’t be a straight road, or the very
powerful statement that רב אשי Rav Ashi says, we might as well
pick up from that at top of דף קוף עמוד א. daf
kuf amud alef. רב אשי אמר כל מן הצד דרך עקלקלות היא,
Rav Ashi amar kol min hatzad derech akalkalot hi, anything that is
off to a side, even if it’s a perfectly straight road, is
an out-of-the-way road, is a, you know,
is an indirect path. Why is that? קרוב לזה ורחוק לזה, karov
lezeh verachok lezeh, any change affects some people positively and some people
negatively. You move the road here, it might look totally straight and
totally convenient, but it’s more convenient for the people living on this
side and less convenient for the people living on that side. So
therefore any type of swap since nobody represents the רבים, rabbim, since
it’s unilateral, is fundamentally invalid and unacceptable. Which then raises the question,
okay fine, so we get why it’s not going, why they keep
their main road here, but then why do they also get the
new one that you just gave them? Right? If the whole swap
was not valid. So that’s the גמרא's gemara question. לימא להו, lema
lehu, so why can’t now the owner say to the, to you
know, the community, שקולו דידכו, shkulu didchu, so keep your old road,
והוי דידי, vehavvei didi, and give me back mine, because the whole
swap didn't, wasn't valid? So the גמרא gemara says הא מני רבי
אליעזר היא, ha meni Rabbi Eliezer hi, so our משנה mishna that
says that they get both follows the position of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi
Eliezer. Which רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? דתניא, detanya, we taught in a
ברייתא, braita, רבי יהודה אומר משום רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Yehuda omer mishum
Rabbi Eliezer, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said in the name of רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, רבים שביררו דרך לעצמם, rabbim sheberu derech leatzmam, if
the masses, you know, the community, just chose a road for themselves
in somebody’s field, מה שביררו ביררו, ma sheberu beru, so it’s good,
they can take it and they can take possession of it. So
just on the simple face of it that sounds bizarre, right? Everybody
gets together and starts walking through, you know, somebody’s field and all
of a sudden it belongs to them? I mean I guess it’s
eminent domain, but you know, it’s not like the government that uses
it at its very sort of limited discretion, and so everybody starts
walking through and now it’s theirs? Really? Is that really true?
So the גמרא gemara says, רבי אליעזר רבנן גזלנים נינהו? Rabbi Eliezer
rabbanan gazlanim ninhu? What? The masses are like thieves, are robbers? They
can just go ahead and do that and without any basis for
it? A, would they be doing such a thing, and B, why
would we legitimate it? So the גמרא gemara says, אמר רב גידל
אמר רב, amar Rav Gidel amar Rav, כגון שאבדה להם דרך באותה
שדה. kegon sheavda lahem derech beoto sadeh. And this actually works very
well with the phrase ביררו. beru. No, no, no, we don’t mean
that they just סתם stam started walking through somebody’s yard and now
it’s theirs. It means they had an established path through somebody’s yard,
however they established it, okay, but they had always had that road
through somebody’s yard, and think of it like a dirt path, and
then you know, one, then it gets lost. How does it get
lost? It’s a rainy season or whatever, the place gets muddy and
swampy and you can’t find where that old road was. So in
that case, since they basically have legal rights to a path through
the guy’s, through the guy’s yard, they can select, and the word
ביררו beru now is very good. They are selecting, meaning you select,
you have a couple of choices, you know the whole, selecting is
you’re entitled to one, you pick from a number of possibilities. So
they have rights to a path, they select a path, and now
that’s theirs, right? So you can, that’s not this case. So but
you can understand that, they’re entitled to one, maybe by a יחיד
yachid we wouldn’t say that, maybe by a יחיד, yachid, I don’t
know, we’d say המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, hamotzi mechavero alav haraya, or
you know, maybe it would be up to the בעל הבית baal
habayit to decide which path
to give the other guy, you know, if you have a question
where’s that path you had in my property, I would say, well,
המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, hamotzi mechavero alav haraya, I’ll choose one, not
you choose one. But somehow because it’s the authority of the רבים,
rabbim, they get to choose. Fine, okay, that’s all very nice, but
fundamentally they’re entitled to it. That doesn’t explain why in this case,
where the whole swap was invalid, why they get to keep the
new road that was given to them even though it was fundamentally
was not a valid swap, okay? So the רשב"ם rashbam tries to
say, well, it’s somewhat similar because at least here the בעל הבית
baal habayit at least initially gave them this willingly. Fine, but he
gave them it willingly under false assumptions or under something that in
the end was invalid. They're retaining their original rights. So it really
does not explain the comparison. So we're going to continue; the גמרא's
Gemara going to give a different explanation for our משנה. Mishnah. Okay?
Well, תוספות Tosafos basically says that that's why the גמרא Gemara at
this stage is eventually going to reject this, because there's not a
good basis for comparison. Okay, so this is just a הוה אמינא
havah amina at this stage. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: אי הכי. I hachi. Now, before we get on to explaining
our משנה, Mishnah, but we're just saying that רב Rav said that
was the case of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, that they lost their
road and they're selecting one. So אמאי אמר רב בר רב הונא
אמר רב? amai amar Rav bar Rav Huna amar Rav? Why do
we have another statement in the name of רב Rav of אין
הלכה כרבי אליעזר? ein halacha k'Rabbi Eliezer? We don't rule like רבי
אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. I mean, if that's the explanation of רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, that he's only talking in a case where they lost
the path and they're selecting a new one, so then רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer is imminently understandable. So why, why would רב, Rav, who
explains רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer in that way, פסקן pasken against him?
So the גמרא Gemara says: Yeah fine, מאן דמתני הא לא מתני
הא. ma'an d'masni ha lo masni ha. There are two versions of
רב. Rav. One version of רב Rav explains רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
in an understandable context, that they lost the path and they're selecting
one, and according to that version רב Rav would rule like רבי
אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. And then there's another version of רב Rav where
רב Rav thinks רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is just saying סתם, stam,
like we were astounded with before. רבים rabbim start walking through my
yard and they get to keep it. So if that's what רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is saying, that the רבים rabbim can do something
like that, you know, without, without any sort of legitimate basis, and
it's still theirs, according to that read of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
רב Rav rules against רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. So either רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer is saying a radical statement and רב Rav rules against
him—that's one version of רב—or Rav that we say רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer is talking about a reasonable sort of circumstances where they lost
the path and they're selecting it, and according to that version, רב
Rav rules like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Fine. So that's רבי אליעזר.
Rabbi Eliezer. But now back to our משנה. Mishnah. So right now
we quoted this idea that the רבים rabbim can select the path,
but the only way that makes sense is if they lost a
path, otherwise we would reject that position. So does that really work
in our משנה? Mishnah? So let's keep on reading, because our משנה,
Mishnah, as we just said, is not that case. So the גמרא
Gemara says, okay, וטעמא מאי? v'ta'ama mai? So then the גמרא Gemara
says, okay, but what's the reason of our משנה? Mishnah? Now, this
is where, you know, תוספות Tosafos basically says didn't the גמרא Gemara
just say it was רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? So this is where
תוספות Tosafos says that what the גמרא's Gemara really saying is that
like okay, like now that you said that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
only makes sense if they lost a path, then that's not relevant
to our משנה. Mishnah. Our משנה, Mishnah, they have their old path.
So what's, what's, give me a better explanation for the משנה? Mishnah?
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer doesn't make
sense. Okay. וטעמא מאי? v'ta'ama mai? So what is the explanation of
our משנה? Mishnah? So
the גמרא Gemara says, משום דרב יהודה. mishum d'Rav Yehuda. Because of
what רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said. דאמר רב יהודה, d'amar Rav Yehuda,
מצר שהחזיקו בו רבים, meitzar she'hecheziku bo rabbim, a path that
was that the רבים rabbim have just started using, have taken possession
of, this is the scenario I gave, they started cutting through somebody's
yard. So אסור לקלקלו, asur l'kalkelo, you can no longer go ahead
and destroy it. They basically by, you know, de facto, they have
just seized the rights to it. Now, of course that sounds like
exactly how we rejected רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer before, right? It says
that what? רבים גזלנין נינהו? rabbim gazlanin ninhu? Okay. So the רשב"ם,
Rashbam, without directly addressing it, tries to tone it down a little
bit. And if you look at the רשב"ם Rashbam in the last
of the narrow lines, he says: שהחזיקו בו רבים, she'hecheziku bo rabbim,
שהשוווהו ותקנוהו להלוך. she'hishvuhu v'tiknuhu l'hiluch.
So he describes it not just they started walking through it, but
that they actually like, you know, like the word of חזקה. chazaka.
Like I do a חזקה chazaka in your field to take possession,
it means I fixed it up. So they actually went in and
they started, I don't know, cleaning out the debris, clearing the path,
okay, so that's the type of a חזקה chazaka that's showing ownership.
Okay, so but now, והבעלים ידעו ושתקו. v'haba'alim yadu v'shatku. What he
adds is: you saw, you know, the town people send some workers
to go clear this path in my yard. It was clear that
they were sort of planning on now using it as their path,
you know, the רבים, rabbim, the town, and I saw them clearing
the path and I didn't say anything. So that is implicitly like
a type of a מחילה. mechila. That's what he says. Okay, what
and now, maybe because you thought that you were going to get
that other path? No, no, what he's talking about סתם stam a
case, not yet our case. סתם, stam, I just have my wheat
field. I wake up one morning, I see some guy who's some
construction crew clearing a path. What the heck are you doing? He
says, oh, you know, the town, the city hall, they sent us
here to clear this path. So I don't say anything. Okay, so
I don't say anything, that's basically like a מחילה. mechila. Then you
wonder, maybe if you were in my yard clearing a path and
I'm saying, "Yeah, because I'm going to start going through your yard,"
and I didn't say anything, maybe that should be a מחילה. mechila.
Okay, it's less now the power of the רבים rabbim and it's
more the fact that I'm silent and I don't respond. But that's
what the רשב"ם Rashbam says to try to like tone it down,
and because the גמרא Gemara was so offended by the idea that
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was saying something like this, if they just
take it it's theirs, and here the גמרא Gemara seems to be
saying... Exactly that. They start seizing it and it's theirs. So he
says, well, the owner saw it and didn't respond. Now, how does
that connect to this? Well, it says it's somewhat similar because here
I gave them the right. Now, I gave them the right under
false pretenses or false understanding, but at least now there's some similarity.
They fundamentally don't have a right and there was some of my
complicit involvement, either not responding or actually giving it to them, even
though under
somewhat misunderstanding,
and that's somehow because they're the רבים rabbim is enough to give
them the right. So let's just finish reading the רשב"ם Rashbam and
then I'll take your question, Gloria. He says, אמר לכולהו דודאי לרבים
מחילה. amar lechulehu devadei lerabbim mechila. So the idea דודאי לרבים מחילה
devadei lerabbim mechila means if it was like just Michael making a
path through my thing, we wouldn't say my silence is a מחילה.
mechila. Okay, it's still my property. But if it's a רבים, rabbim,
we do. So since I'm a little bit complicit in my silence,
that's seen as like that makes it theirs. וכל שכן מתניתין vechol
sheken matnitin and now he wants to apply it to our משנה,
mishna, he says וכל שכן, vechol sheken, I don't know if I'd
say וכל שכן, vechol sheken, שנתנו להם ההוא דרך בידיים. shenatnu lahem
hahu derech biyadayim.
When you actively gave it to them, even though it might have
been under false understanding that you would be it would be a
legitimate swap, but you gave something to the רבים, rabbim, we're going
now interpret that in favor of the רבים rabbim that you wanted
them to have it regardless. הלכך מה שנתן נתן, hilchach mah shenatan
natan, but then he adds a phrase, וכגון שהחזיקו. ukegon shehechiziku. But
even that, when it says that now they get this, it would
be limited to a case where they actually physically took possession of
it. It wasn't just you did the swap. They would have to
have done something that would have shown their rights to it, their
de facto presence. So either they fix it up, like he said
החזיקו hechiziku meant they like clear the path and they lay some
gravel or whatever they do, or maybe they just start walking. We'll
talk about just walking in a minute. Okay, so that's the way
he explained it, similar to what we said before. Yeah, because it's
רבים rabbim they get it even though it's not theirs. But the
way now we've toned it down a little bit is we've said,
and because you are complicit in it, similar
to how we're explaining this statement of רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, therefore
we assume you're okay with them having it and they actually physically
took possession, you didn't just say that they had it. Gloria, you've
been waiting patiently. Is there something similar in US law where if
you constantly let somebody take a shortcut through your property, they end
up getting an easement, which is like a right of way? And
that's why they
post trespassers will be prosecuted on
property, so that if you happen to be doing it and I'm
not paying attention, it's very clear that I'm not מוחל, mochel, I'm
not, that's a good
point. Right, so to some degree that came up in the earlier
פרקים, prakim, all that stuff about חזקה chazaka of three years, and
if I start doing things and you don't start saying anything, then
implicitly you're giving me the right to do it. Right, I start
having barbecues in my yard and put smoke in yours and you
haven't said anything, so it's like right, but then if that's true,
wouldn't it be like limited to the רבים? rabbim? So there's something
here that is basically implicitly saying if we're just an individual doing
this, it would not have been
considered either under a long enough duration or drastic enough that by
itself would have given him rights, but because it's רבים rabbim we
say that it does. But yeah, I mean it does play into
ideas of מחילה mechila that we've had before. Yes. So again, so
the fact that he's doing it only because he's בטעות, beta'ut, that
makes no difference then? Right, that's what we say, which again to
me is like it's a big difference when I'm under false assumptions
as opposed to I know the רבים rabbim is cutting through my
yard and I'm not saying anything. It's very clear to me what's
going on and I'm being okay with it. As opposed to here,
it's doing I'm only giving it to them because I'm making certain
assumptions which turn out to be false. But he didn't voice those
assumptions and point out like I'm doing this. He did voice those
assumptions, I'll give you this and I'll take that. All right, anyway,
but this is what we're sort of coming to conclusion which is
pretty similar to what we said before about רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
but then we were offended and we said רבים גזלנים, rabbim gazlanim,
and here somehow we've come to terms with its restatement by the
name of רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. There was the added word of
חזקה, chazaka, which means they've actually done something active to show their
ownership and somehow we're assuming that the owners are somewhat complicit or
silent or whatever. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
רבי
אליעזר, רבים במאי קנו לה? Rabbi Eliezer, rabbim bemai kanu leh? So
back to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says if they just select
it. So how do they select it? What did they verbally that
means it's theirs now? Let's say it's the case of אבדה להם
שדה, avda lahem sade, that they lost the path and then they
get to select a new one. But what does it mean? Just
selecting is an act of taking possession? How did they take possession?
So the גמרא Gemara says בהילוכה, behilucha, they actually by walking. Yes,
the act of walking. Now again remember the רשב"ם Rashbam said a
minute ago of רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, which was a similar statement,
that חזקה chazaka meant like classic חזקה, chazaka, they fixed the path.
But here since רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda didn't use that word, he
just says selected, they say for him even walking is a taking
of possession. וכהא דתניא, vehacha detanya, well, okay, so the רשב"ם Rashbam
says that but he says that would be when it's fixed by
stomping on it. But here you're just using it.
דתניא דתנן. detanya detnan. הלך בה לאורכה ולרוחבה, Halach bah le'orka u'lerochba,
that might signify anything for people from biblically?
Okay, if you right right especially. Oh, it talks about פרשת Parshas
too, look at that. Okay, if somebody has, if somebody walked a
field its length and its width,
so the גמרא Gemara says, הלך בה לאורכה ולרוחבה קנה מקום הילוכה
דברי רבי אליעזר. Halach bah le'orka u'lerochba kana mekom hilucho divrei Rebbi
Eliezer. So it's the same רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, there's a completely
different discussion, not a case of רבים. Rabbin. I'm trying to sell
something to Michael, I sell him my field, and he walks the
perimeter. So רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer says, okay, it's not a קניין
kinyan on the whole field, but it's a קניין kinyan on the
perimeter because that's because the act of walking is actually an act
of חזקה. chazaka. Okay, that's what רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer says, and
certainly that would work in the case of the path. וחכמים אומרים,
VeChachamim omrim, the Sages say, אין הילוך מועיל כלום עד שיחזיק. ein
hiluch mo'il klum ad she'yachazik. No,
you need to do classic חזקה, chazaka, which is an act of
like improving it, not just walking on it. אמר רב אלעזר, Amar
Reb Elazar, says רב אלעזר, Reb Elazar, not רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer,
the אמורא Amora רב אלעזר. Reb Elazar. מאי טעמא דרבי אליעזר, Mai
ta'ama deRebbi Eliezer, what is his reason? דכתיב, Dechsiv, the verse says,
קום התהלך בארץ לאורכה ולרוחבה, kum hishalech ba'aretz le'orka u'lerochba, the length
and the width, okay so כי לך אתננה. ki lecha etnenah. So
you see that's an act of taking possession. Of course, from that
you would get a sense that walking the perimeter is an act
of taking possession on the whole thing, okay, but anyway he assumes
that אברהם's Avraham's walking through the land was a type of a
חזקה chazaka on the land. He wasn't like necessarily digging it and
improving it, etc. He was more or less, you know, with sheep
and a nomad, so he wasn't actually like settling and planting the
land, you know, but nevertheless it's an act of חזקה. chazaka. And
certainly, by the way, in a case where it's a path, you
know, if walking on a path, which is exactly the standard use,
you could say walking around the perimeter of a wheat field isn't
a חזקה. chazaka. But walking on a path could be a חזקה.
chazaka. That gets to an interesting question of when do we say
the using something is a חזקה chazaka as opposed to the classic
חזקה chazaka of land of taking possession, you might remember is improving
it. Building a fence, making an opening into a fence, right, planting
it or whatever, but would using it for, you know, taking from
it, using it, be a חזקה? chazaka? Sometimes it would. That was
discussed earlier. So if we're talking about a path, it makes a
lot of sense, but רבי אליעזר's Rebbi Eliezer's not even limiting himself
to that position. Okay, so let's take a look what the גמרא
Gemara says. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: ורבנן, VeRabbanan, and
the Rabbis that say it wasn't a חזקה chazaka that אברהם Avraham
did not take legal ownership of the land by doing that, so
התם משום חביבותא דאברהם הוא. hasam mishum chavivusa deAvraham hu. That's because
of the God's like love of אברהם Avraham דקאמר ליה הכי. deka'amar
lei hachi. He said, God said this to him, כדי שיהא נוח
לכבוש לפני בניו. kedei she'yei noach lichvosh lifnei banav. So the land
should be easy for his descendants to conquer. So what does that
mean? So it sort of sounds like the classic idea of מעשה
אבות סימן לבנים, ma'aseh avos siman labanim, you know, that because the
forefathers do something, that lays the, you know, the groundwork, the metaphysical
groundwork as it were, for the thing to happen in the future.
So you know, אברהם Avraham goes down to
מצרים Mitzrayim and then he comes back with all this wealth, so
his children go down to מצרים Mitzrayim and then they come out
with all this wealth. So it sort of it like prefigures, but
not just prefigures, that's a literary term which just means it sends
the signal that it's going to happen. It actually has some causal
impact, you know, makes it so that it lays the, the metaphysically
the reality so that this can now happen for the descendants. So
אברהם Avraham is like walking through the land and that's going to
make it more possible for his descendants to take that type of
possession of the land. That's what I would have said, it's a
type of מעשה אבות סימן לבנים. ma'aseh avos siman labanim. The רשב"ם
Rashbam says something slightly different, which is interesting, saying okay, it's not
a legal act of taking possession, but it's still sort of, you
know, it's still sort of a symbolically demonstrating a sense of possession
which now will make it easier for that to happen for his
children. I mean metaphysically, it's sort of like, you know, he's possessing
it, I mean he didn't really do it so then... That's what
I mean, symbolically it shows possession even though legally it's not. Like
a sort of almost like כביכול kiveyakol the beginning of the כיבוש,
kibbush, like in a very, you know, benign way, which sort of
makes it, you know, then already in our national psyche so to
speak. Oh, so that's a different explanation, not a metaphysical one. You're
just sort of saying like because you know, our, like you know,
we sort of have that, you know, our way of looking at
sort of אברהם Avraham and giving us a sense of connection to
the land.
You're explaining the metaphysical aspect more psychologically, which is a good point.
If you look at the רשב"ם, Rashbam, the רשב"ם Rashbam says like
this, the first widest line of the רשב"ם: Rashbam: כדי שיהא נוח,
Kedei she'yei noach, דהוו להו כיורשים ולא כגזלנים, dehavu lehu kiyorshim velo
kegazlanim, ולא יהא רשות לשטן לקטרג, velo yehei reshus leSatan lekatreg, ולא
פתחון פה לבעל מידת הדין. velo pis'chon peh leba'al middas hadin.
Which obviously takes on a lot of weight in contemporary political context,
right, that it's their... oh, now so he says it's not psychological,
it's not metaphysical, it's more like a statement to the, to every,
it's sort of like that first רש"י Rashi on the תורה, Torah,
right? It's like a, you know, it's like a statement to the
world. It's like look, we have it by rights, we have it
as, you know, אברהם Avraham had it, we're getting it from אברהם
Avraham and so on. Of course it's ironic, because if it's not
an act of חזקה... chazaka... and it wasn't an act of taking
possession, how it makes us like יורשים, yorshim, but it makes you
feel that way, okay, that we have it sort of as an
inheritance.
But at least Michael explained that psychologically, if this is in order
to respond to an outside critique, I'm not sure how good of
a response that's gonna be, you know, but anyway, very interesting that
line in the גמרא Gemara in the contemporary political context. Okay, so
now we continue. So גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רבי יוסי
בר חנינא מודים חכמים לרבי אליעזר בשביל של כרמים, Amar Rabbi Yosei
bar Chanina modim chachamim l'Rabbi Eliezer b'shvil shel kramim, so this is
what I alluded to before. He says they would agree to Rabbi
Eliezer that a simple walking would be an act of חזקה chazakah
if we were dealing with like a narrow path through a vineyard.
Why? הואיל ונעשה להילוך נקנה בהילוך, ho'il v'na'aseh l'hiluch nikneh b'hiluch, since
its entire function is just to walk through it, that's how it's
taking possession. And again the רשב"ם Rashbam refers to an earlier discussion
in the גמרא Gemara that in some cases when something has like
you know, it's like the גמרא Gemara spoke about like hard rock.
What are you supposed to do on hard rock? How you supposed
to plant it? How you supposed to do a חזקה? chazakah? So
using it, like using it to lay out your you know, your
laundry or something might be a חזקה chazakah when something has no
real other way of doing a חזקה. chazakah. Okay, so here too
it seems that you know, we're saying sometimes using it is a
חזקה, chazakah, so the חכמים chachamim would agree if something that's only
made for being a path, then there actually walking on it would
be a חזקה. chazakah. So presumably the earlier discussion about cutting through
the wheat field or whatever, since primarily it's a wheat field, even
though what you want from it is to have a path through
it, a חזקה chazakah of walking would not be enough according to
the חכמים. chachamim. But if something is clearly a path and only
a path, then maybe they would agree that that's an act of
חזקה. chazakah. Let me see if I understand. Let's say you have
a huge vineyard. Yeah. And you want to get into town and
you as an owner created a path so that you can get
into town. Right. Now you have a huge piece of property, people
are using it, you don't know they're using it because you're off
somewhere else. Right. So you have to hire Gloria as your lawyer
and you'll put up signs that say trespassers will be prosecuted. I
mean, but you're right, like how much is this idea of רבים
שהחזיקו בו, rabim she'hecheziku bo, how much does it go because of
the sort of weight we give to the fact of the רבים,
rabim, a type of almost an eminent domain type of thing you
know, seems to be like a subtle component of this. How much
does that mean that you know, that we'll readily... we'll be very
prepared to interpret it in their favor, you know, how much you
need to be there and not saying anything, are we just going
to assume that you're okay with it unless we have evidence
otherwise? Right, the גמרא Gemara never sort of fully spells that out.
If it's the open community they can just walk through anywhere they
want. I understand. Then everybody will start putting up fences, what do
I tell you. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. כי
אתו לקמיה דרבי יצחק בר אמי אמרו להו הבו ליה כהיכא דדרי
טונא דשבישתא והדר. Ki atu l'kamei d'Rabbi Yitzchak bar Ami amru lehu
havu lei k'heicha d'dari tuna d'shavishta v'hadar.
So when people came to Rabbi Yitzchak bar Ami, now what was
the case? We seem not to be going back to the like
the more standard case of our משנה mishnah which is you know,
because the משנה mishnah says דרך היחיד ארבע אמות, derech hayachid arba
amot,
that a path of an individual, if I sell Michael, Michael I'll
sell you a path through my yard, a private path through my
yard, so the minimum width would be four אמות. amot. So now
the גמרא Gemara says that some people would come to Rav Ami
and it was a case where they bought a path, if this
is one way of explaining the case, and the question was how
wide of the path... how wide was it? So according to our
משנה mishnah it should have been four אמות, amot, or it could
be they lost a path and they were trying to establish a
new one. Okay, but something of that nature. And he gave them
how much width did he give them? He said give them the
width of what actually, no, the reason excuse me, the reason it's
not the four אמות amot of our משנה mishnah is I think
that it was a case of a vineyard path. Let me just
check the רשב"ם. Rashbam.
Yeah, so the רשב"ם Rashbam says it was a vineyard path, which
might be narrower than... you like you know the whole thing by
Bilaam, might be משעול הכרמים גדר מזה וגדר מזה, mishol hakramim gader
mizeh v'gader mizeh, when the donkey goes through the vineyard path it's
like very narrow and there's walls on both sides and there's nowhere
to turn. So the רשב"ם Rashbam says it's a vineyard path, which
might explain why it's not necessarily four אמות, amot, might be narrower.
The רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel at least explains that it's talking about
a path through a field. Okay, but so I'm going to read
it. So הבו ליה, havu lei, so he said give to him
כהיכא דדרי טונא, k'heicha d'dari tuna, the amount of width that he
could be carrying like a load of wood on his back דשבישתא,
d'shavishta, okay, right, right, and והדר, v'hadar, and to turn around. So
it's like what you say, what you say? So there's got to
be a little turning room, maybe to turn around and go back.
Okay, but basically that width of a guy carrying... what שבישתא shavishta
mean? What? שבישתא shavishta is... is sticks. דדרי טונא דשבישתא, d'dari tuna
d'shavishta, excuse me, thank you. A bundle of sticks, right, a bundle
of sticks, והדר, v'hadar, and then turn. לא אמרן, lo amran, now
what is that true? אלא דמסיימי מחיצתא, ela d'mesaymi mechitza,
only if the walls are actually like you know, like defined, okay,
then because apparently the point is that if you've got tall walls,
the way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains it means you've got tall walls,
then you need the path to be a certain width because if
the path is narrower, I'm not going to be able to get
through with my sticks. So if you've got walls, you've got to
give me... that width. Okay. Four אמות, amos, that's like six to
eight feet.
Right, so the משנה Mishna says four אמות, amos, this is a
different measure. So that's why, that's what I said, this measure might
be narrower because a vineyard path might be assumed to be a
narrower path than a field path. Right, eight feet, if let's say
six feet, it's one, two, three, four, five, six. It's the wall
to here. It's not so much. I mean, it doesn't sound like
there's a big difference between four אמות amos and carrying a pile
of wood, maybe. Depends how wide the pile of wood is. Okay,
but four אמות amos is from this wall to here. Yeah, the
doorway is about three. Yeah. So that's probably, that's probably a good,
a somewhat more than just the pile of wood width. Anyway, so
he said that's only that you need to have it that width
if you've got walls, because then the walls, like, ממש, mamash, it's
like the story by בלעם, Bilam, the walls make it that you
can't move. So you need that width to get through with your,
with your sticks. והדר, v'hadar, and then ולא אמרן אלא דמסיימי מחיצה.
v'lo amran ela d'mesayem mechitza. But ולא אמרן v'lo amran if there
are no walls, then כי היכי דשקיל כרעא ומנח כרעא, ki haychi
d'shakil kara u'manach kara, then it could be like single file, just
as much to like put my foot forward and my next foot
forward, you know, just enough for the space, for the width of
my feet, because then, okay, I've got this big thing, but who
cares? My, the path is where my feet are going to be
going. So if I'm carrying a big thing, but there's no walls
in the way, then you don't have to give me a wide
path, you can give me a very narrow path. Right? I mean,
I have to learn to walk a straight line, almost. But yes.
Okay. But anyway, what's not clear is why is this different than
our משנה? Mishna? Four אמות... amos... it might be again, because we're
specifically talking about a vineyard. All right.
כרעא kara is a foot, a leg. Yeah. Okay.
Okay. So now the... yeah, there's one quick question. In terms of
the חזקה, chazaka, like if you don't say it's הילוך, illuk, but
it's תיקון, tikun, does he have to be תיקון tikun across the
whole path or just like a little part of it, and that's
like symbolic of the whole thing? So let's say he just does
תיקון tikun in the middle. Yeah, no, no, yeah, what we learned
before is that even a little bit if it's all considered one
unit. Okay. דרך היחיד ארבע אמות. derech hayachid arba amos. Now that's
in the משנה, Mishna, if I sell somebody a private path through
my field, so I give him, it's four אמות amos wide again,
as we said, different than what we just said about the vineyard
path. תנא, אחרים אומרים כדי שיעבור חמור במשאו. tanna, acheirim omrim k'dei
sheyavor chamor b'masa'o.
There's a ברייתא Baraisa that has an opposing position that it's the
amount of width that a donkey can pass through with its bundle,
with its, you know, load, very similar to what we just talked
about the sticks and the person with the vineyard. אמר רב הונא
הלכה כאחרים. amar Rav Huna halacha k'acheirim. We rule like אחרים. acheirim.
דייני גולה אומרים Diyanei Gola omrim or whatever they said, שתי גמדים
ומחצה, shtei gmadim u'mechetza, two...
now גמדים gmadim is another word for an אמה. ama. For so
two and a half אמה ama as opposed to four אמות. amos.
Why do they say גמדים gmadim now instead of אמה? ama? So
the רשב"ם Rashbam says maybe it means a slightly larger אמה ama
or then he says it may mean a slightly smaller אמה, ama,
I don't know. But it's some different variation of an אמה. ama.
The רמבּ"ם Rambam just paskens straight הלכה halacha of אמה. ama. So
it's not four אמות, amos, it's two and a half אמות. amos.
Maybe that is closer now to the whole thing before about the
vineyard. They're getting to sound to be much, to be close. ואמר
רב הונא הלכה כדייני גולה. v'amar Rav Huna halacha k'Diyanei Gola. We
rule like that against our משנה. Mishna. ואמר רב הונא הלכה כאחרים.
v'amar Rav Huna halacha k'acheirim. Don't we just say we rule like
אחרים, acheirim, that it's the width of a donkey with its load?
האי והאי שיעורא חד הוא. hai v'hai shiura chad hu. That's exactly
the load of the width of a donkey with its load. They're
just giving that amount. It's two and a half אמות amos against
the ruling of our משנה. Mishna. Okay, דרך הרבים שש עשרה אמה.
derech harabim shesh esrei ama. If I sell a path for the
רבים rabim through my, through my field, then I then they have
16 אמות, amos, which is like 24 feet. תנו רבנן: דרך היחיד
ארבע אמות, דרך מעיר לעיר. tanu rabbanan: derech hayachid arba amos, derech
me'ir l'ir. Let's say I sell to these townspeople a path through
my field to get from one town to the next town. So
it's not going to be used by, you know, the larger world,
it's just going to be used by people in Town A and
Town B to connect the two towns. Okay, so it's more obviously
than a יחיד, yachid, but it's not yet the size of the
רבים. rabim. It's not going to be used from anybody outside of
the two towns. Okay.
So דרך מעיר לעיר שמונה אמות. derech me'ir l'ir shemoneh amos. That
would be eight אמות. amos. דרך הרבים, derech harabim, however, if it's
actually something that's going to be used by, you know, anybody from
the larger world that's coming to our town is going to take
this road and cut, you know, that cut through my wheat field.
By the way, you really begin to understand this, because the wheat
fields were right, the fields were outside the town, right? I mean,
that's where, that's where you would build your road, right? Like here's
your little town, right? Here's where everybody has their big wheat fields,
right? You know, all their, you know, all of that stuff is
like around the town, right? That's, so then anyway, where else are
you going to build your road except through the wheat field? So,
all right, so in that case, where it's a road that's going
to be used by not just to connect two towns, but that's
going to be used by like anybody who's coming to this town
or going out of this town or whatever to the larger world,
that has to be bigger, שש עשרה אמה. shesh esrei ama. דרך
ערי מקלט, derech arei miklat, now if they're roads that are leading
to the ערי מקלט arei miklat where you want them, you know,
תכין לך הדרך, tachin lecha haderech, right? The פסוק pasuk says you
have to make it very accessible. Okay, so therefore that extra emphasis
of תכין לך הדרך tachin lecha haderech means that it has to
be even like larger. I don't know, maybe it means it's better
maintained. I would think so too, anyway. Or maybe maybe easier access
to get to those roads too. Anyway, דרך ערי מקלט derech arei
miklat שלושים
ושתיים אמות shloshim ushtayim amot 32 twice the width, right? That's pretty
darn big. That's what's that's like that's like 50 feet. How what's
the width of a standard what's a high what's a highway? That's
what I was thinking like for that? I don't know, yeah. I
don't know how many a highway is. One lane, one lane is
like what? I don't know, is it? I don't know, somebody look
it up on Google. Anyway, that's like 50 feet. And how wide
is a wagon? A wagon, a wagon was right, a single wagon
was like ארבע אמות, arba amot, which is why a דרך היחיד
derech hayachid was said before to have been ארבע אמות, arba amot,
right? Like a multi-wagon caravan is obviously a whole different story. אמר
רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, מאי קרא? mai kra? What do you
learn from פסוק? pasuk? דכתיב dechtiv תכין לך הדרך. tachin lecha haderech.
דרך הדרך. derech haderech. So one way of reading it is the
extra ה hei of הדרך, haderech, although I would have just read
it from the תכין לך, tachin lecha, you know, that it has
to be extra
attention paid to it. דרך המלך אין לו שיעור. derech hamelech ein
lo shiur. A king's way has no limit. שהמלך פורץ גדר לעשות
לו דרך ואין מוחין בידו shehamelech poretz geder la'asot lo derech ve'ein
mochin beyado for the king basically, as we said the other day,
it's good to be king, a king basically can just burst through
and make his own path and nobody can prevent him. Now the
okay one second, now the so what does that have to do
with our discussion? Our discussion until now had been about selling a
path through your field. How do you sell a path through your
field to the king and then he can have as much as
he wants? Like what does that mean? So one way to explain
this is we're no longer dealing with selling a path. We're just
telling the הלכה. halacha. If a king marches in through town, he
gets to knock down any structure to get where he's going and
nobody can protest it. Okay, but רמב"ם Rambam actually פוסק paskens no.
It means that you made a deal with, you know, you sold
something to the castle there, you know, to the to the king
and you sold them a path through your field. And then the
question is okay how big did they get? And the רשב"ם Rashbam
says and the רמב"ם Rambam says well there's no well no interestingly
he says there's we don't know the exact amount and since we
don't know the exact amount he says it's like a case of
selling something to somebody without being able to identify what it was
that you sold. And the רמב"ם Rambam doesn't actually say the final
line but the נושאי כלים nosei keilim say that according to the
רמב"ם Rambam the king wouldn't get anything because since you don't know
how much you get nothing which is like completely bizarre. Anyway, the
ראב"ד Ra'avad says no it means that the king gets to say
what he takes. Which is like so don't make a deal like
that with the castle. Spell it out more specifically what exactly you're
selling. Okay, but it is interesting that they're trying to read this
in the context of the משנה mishna that you sold it to
the king. But then leaves the question what does it mean that
you sell something to someone and they can take as much as
they want? But מיכה Micha what what do you have for us?
12 feet is a standard lane so so 32 אמות amot is
like a four-lane highway or something like that?
But you need a little bit space for two whatever. It's like
a four-lane highway and shoulder. Shoulder.
Okay got it. All right. Okay. דרך הקבר
אין לה שיעור. derech hakever ein lah shiur.
And again רמב"ם Rambam and ראב"ד Ra'avad read that this is also
talking about that I sold somebody a path through my through my
field in order to get to their family grave or whatever it
is. We're going to deal with family grave coming up. So again
how do you deal with the sale when you don't know the
amount? Okay but the other way to read it is just it's
not telling you a question of sale it's just telling you a
הלכה. halacha. People are coming through town they're carrying a grave or
whatever they have a right to sort of cut through people's fields
to get to the burial. משום יקרא
דשכבי mishum yikra deshichvi
because of honor to the dead body to the dead. Like compassion.
Right although so the word it uses is honor. You're honoring the
dead because you're allowing many people to sort of crowd. If everybody
had to go single file whatever right it's a bigger honor to
come in a large entourage of people and so on. So it's
really more I think honor is more the relevant term. Okay המעמד.
hamamad. Now let's say I sell somebody in my field a place
for doing מעמדות. ma'amadot. מעמד ma'amad as we're going to see is
a certain practice that was done after the body was buried of
rising and sitting and rising and sitting and of saying maybe certain
words of either consolation or words of eulogy. And I am selling
somebody like got this field that's near wherever the graveyard is and
a space in my field to do this ritual. Okay for people
that are returning from the graveyard. Again one way to understand this
is that they have a family grave nearby. A family we're going
to see they had these caves where they had you know and
whatever and this is near their family grave and they want to
buy this part in my field. So it doesn't say what the
parameters are. So it says well what was it? שדה בית פרס
היא בית ארבע קבין sadeh beit peras hi beit arba kavin the
space of ארבע קבין arba kavin which is a I said before
a what do you call it a standard sort of you know
size of of land is a בית סאה beit se'ah which is
50 by 50 אמות. amot. Okay so and a סאה se'ah is
שש קבין. shesh kavin. So בית ארבע קבין beit arba kavin is
two-thirds of that. Okay so it's two-thirds of a בית סאה. beit
se'ah.
So for a בית סאה... beit se'ah... is 2500 square אמות, amos,
what would be two-thirds of that?
What's two-thirds of 25? 50 divided by 3 is about 16 and
change. Okay, so that's about 1600 and whatever, I think like 66
square אמות. amos. It's pretty large. What would that be? That would
be about 40 by 40 square אמות. amos. Yeah, a little bit
more than 40 by 40 square אמות. amos. 60 feet by 60
feet. That's a pretty large space, right? Okay, so that's what it
is. It's about 40 אמות, amos, 40 by 40 אמות, amos, okay,
which is about 60 feet by 60 feet.
That's about the size. What's a yard? That would be a yard,
what would that be, 20 yards? 400 square yards. Okay, so now,
so that's this מעמד. maamad. Now
תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, I'm sorry, yeah, תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. אין
פוחתין, ein pochtin, now we're going to discuss this process, I'm sorry,
I skipped a line. Where were we? מעמד, maamad, תנו רבנן. tanu
rabbanan. המוכר קברו דרך קברו מקום מעמדו בית הספדו. Hamocher kivro derech
kivro mekom maamado beis hespedo.
Now, let's say somebody went ahead and they sold, their family had
this, you know, they had a grave purchased in a, now you
know, in a, you know, in a field, which is where they
were going to be buried, or they owned the path through the
field to the grave, or they owned this place, you know, in
somebody else's field for the מעמדות, maamadot, or a place where they
would actually do the הספדים, hespedim, so presumably the הספדים hespedim would
be like before the מעמד, maamad, that would be the eulogies and
they bury and then they would do the מעמד. maamad. So anyway,
all this stuff was owned by this person to be ready for,
you know, his eventual death that they'd be able to use this
by his family when they were to be put him to rest.
And he went ahead and he was hard up for money, so
he went ahead and he sold it, cause he needed like, he
needed to live right now, so he sold his, so he sold
his, his grave. So what's the הלכה? halacha? באין בני משפחה וקוברים
אותו על כרחו. Bain bnei mishpacha vekovrin oso al korcho.
So after he dies, the family members can come and basically retake
possession of those places and bury their, you know, father, brother, whoever.
Why? משום פגם משפחה. mishum pgam mishpacha. It would be an embarrassment
to the family that their person, that their, you know, father, let's
say, would have no place to be buried. And of course the
point is, so what about the guy who bought it, right? Can
he get it back afterwards? So he, no, well that, you could
say that maybe for the מעמד, maamad, but it doesn't work for
the קבר. kever. Okay, so the הלכה halacha is at least anyway
that the guy, so maybe you're right, so like things that are
just a one-time, like a use and then they can go back,
but at least for the קבר kever whatever, they basically they pay
the person who bought it, but they forcibly take repossession of it
and pay the person who bought, pay back the person who bought
it. So it's really not smart to buy, so you do what
אברהם Avraham did, you buy a cave and you turn it into
a קבר. kever. You don't buy actually somebody's place that's already been
designated as a קבר. kever. Yes. There's also הלכה halacha not to
bury someone where they're expecting to be buried, so there's that place
and it's all of that. Right, yeah, that could be too. I
mean, here it frames it as פגם משפחה, pgam mishpacha, but you're
right, you know? But anyway, it is quite interesting, like 'cause at
one, the question I'm wondering is like if, if what it means
is that you know, this guy's family has a plot here where
all of these, you know, where their whole family, the whole Smith
family is buried here, and this was John Smith's plot and he
sold it away, so then it would be an embarrassment that their,
you know, that one of the members of the family isn't buried
here and some stranger is buried here, right? And then you can
really understand it. So I can understand this a lot, the פגם
משפחה, pgam mishpacha, if it's in the context where it's a person's
grave amongst a family plot. He's turning in his grave! But if
it's a person's grave in some middle of nowhere, right, so why
is it such a פגם משפחה? pgam mishpacha? Go ahead and collect
the money and buy a new grave for your father, you know?
So it makes sense very much when it's in the context of
a family site. Okay, תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. Now we're going to
discuss what this process of מעמדות maamadot is.
אין פוחתין משבעה מעמדות ומושבות Ein pochtin mishiva maamadot umoshavot למת lames
כנגד הבל הבלים אמר קהלת הבל הבלים הכל הבל. keneged hevel havalim
amar Kohelet hevel havalim hakol havel. So it says the word הבל
hevel five times but two of them are in the plural, so
that's seven. Seven times that the world is all nothingness and meaningless,
so it's the sense of like, you know, of mourning, of coming
into contact with like, what does our lives mean? But one minute,
but the רשב"ם Rashbam is interesting. The רשב"ם Rashbam says, you take
a look at the רשב"ם Rashbam where he says what, what were
they doing at this time, so the רשב"ם Rashbam says משבעה מעמדות
ומושבות, mishiva maamadot umoshavot, so if you look at it it's like
two lines under where it says קהלת א Kohelet aleph in the
margins, he says בחזרתם מן הקבר הולכים מעט ויושבים לנחם האבל. bachazirasam
min hakever holchin meat veyoshvin lenachem ha'avel. So he says that actually
they would sit to console the mourner. Now this, the people who
would be doing the מעמדות ומושבות, maamadot umoshavot, we're going to find
out, were relatives of the dead, of the person who passed away,
but not the
the
other participants of
the funeral who are
not the mourners themselves. Wait, but wait a minute, we have a
practice on the way there. No, I know, so we do, I
was going to say that. So what we do is as we're
bringing the מת meis to the to the to the grave, right,
we do, you know, we do that, we sort of we read
a פרק perek in תהילים Tehillim and we stop and then we
start again and we do it seven times. And part of the,
so it clearly seems to be based on a parallel of this.
I don't know if it's an interpretation of this or a parallel
of this. And normally also the sense is to also show like
a reluctance. You know, you don't want to you know to make
to do that final parting with the dead. But yes, we do
have the parallel prior to coming back. Right, we do not. I
mean we do a שורה. shura. I don't know why that, because
we're going to see later it was only a place where they
had the מנהג, minhag, it's not a mandate. It's not a mandate,
it's a practice. Okay, הולכים מעט ויושבים לנחם האבל, holchim me-at ve-yoshvim
lenachem ha-avel,
so one explanation is to do ניחום אבלים. nichum aveilim.
Okay, או להרבות צער המית, o le-harbos tzar ha-meis, or to do
you know to be bemoaning and bewailing which would sort of be
like a הספד hesped would be. By the way, you know our
הספדים hespedim or eulogies are like often like they say like to
celebrate a life but a classic הספד, hesped, like ספוד על ירך
spod al yerech means like to slap, you know, and like אוי
אוי אוי, oy oy oy, like you know and it would be
right בקינה be-kina would be a wailing. I mean I was actually
at you know when Rabbi Katz's father passed away, I was at
that you know the funeral there in the Satmar community and it
made me think exactly of like how it's described in the גמרא.
Gemara. Like you know, it was almost, I don't want to say
this, but there was almost like theatrical, not in the sense that
they didn't, but you know what I mean, like there was a
clear attempt that was like that everybody is going to be doing
this act of ritualized like wailing, you know, and it was, yeah,
it was very powerful. You know, it was not, let's go and
talk about this person's life, but it was everybody was like you
know wailing sort of. So anyway, so one, so it's very different
explanations. One is to do ניחום אבלים nichum aveilim and the other
is to actually to do wailing. או להרבות צער למת שמת ולהרבות
בבכי, o le-harbos tzar le-meis she-meis u-le-harbos be-vechi, ונתנה אשה אל לבה,
ve-nasna isha el libah, and now it's the connection to the הבל
הבלים, hevel havelim, אל לבה לשוב בתשובה, el libah lashuv be-teshuva, כי
חיי אדם הבל. ki chayei adam hevel.
So okay, so that's the הבל הבלים. hevel havelim. You feel oy,
what's the purpose of life and you do תשובה. teshuva. So I
don't know where he sort of starts bringing in the whole תשובה
teshuva mode. Okay, but it does sort of make you sort of,
you know, anyway connect to that sense of like, which is interesting
because you would think after the dead is buried you want to
be focusing on you know on on ניחום, nichum, on consoling. And
you could sort of understand the הבל הבלים hevel havelim not in
a, I mean it says the whole פסוקים pesukim there are very
depressing, but not in a depressing sense, but in a sense like,
you know, ultimately they're going to their better reward. Right, this life
doesn't have is isn't where the true meaning is held is not
in this life but in the future life. You know, so there
could be a way in which that could work with a with
a consoling theme. But anyway, that's not the theme that the רשב"ם
Rashbam here is picking up on. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this.
Okay, we might as well read it. Okay, yeah fine, I'll read
the next line, one minute. Okay, ועומדים והולכים מעט וחוזרים ויושבים מעט,
כך עושים שבע פעמים, ve-omdim ve-holchim me-at ve-chozrim ve-yoshvim me-at, kach osim
sheva pe'amim, כדי לתת אל לבם שחיי אדם הבל, kedei laseis el
libam she-chayei adam hevel, והיינו דמפרש לקמן כנגד שבע הבל הבלים, ve-hainu
de-mefaresh lekaman keneged sheva hevel havelim, שכתוב בראש ספר קהלת. she-kasuv be-rosh
sefer Koheles. כן יראה הטעם בעיני. ken yira'e ha-ta'am be-einai. ואיכא דכתב
מפני שהשדים מתלוים עם החוזרים מבית הקברות. ve-ika de-chasav mipnei she-ha-shedim mislavim
im ha-chozrim mibeis ha-kvaros.
Right, this is this idea like also why we wash our hands
outside the בית הקברות, beis ha-kvaros, you know, somehow the שדים, shedim,
the demons that are there, it's a very dangerous spiritual place, so
they adhere to like stick, cleave to the people that are returning.
Okay, ולכך תיקנו מעמדות ומושבות כדי שבתוך כך יסתלקו השדים מעליהם. u-lechach
tiknu ma'amados u-moshavos kedei she-be-soch kach yistalku ha-shedim me'aleihem.
So you wear them out or you get them tired or bored
or whatever it is and then finally the שדים shedim leave because
you're doing this. Okay, ולא נהירא, דאם כן היו עושים כן בכל
מקום, וכאן אמרינן דבמנהגא תליא מלתא. ve-lo nehira, de-im ken hayu osim
ken be-chol makom, ve-chan amrinan de-be-minhaga talya milta. Then why is it
based on הבל הבלים hevel havelim and why is it based on
מנהג? minhag? It would be something we should do universally. Yes David,
what do you want to say? I just wanted to say there's
a note here of the רש"י Rashi in מגילה Megillah that stated
this was performed on the way to the burial. Oh really? That
would be parallel in what we do. Okay. So thank you, I
had I had forgotten that. Apparently, David just said that according to
a רש"י Rashi in מגילה Megillah they did it on the way
to the burial, which would fit better not only with the fact
that it parallels our what we do, our seven stops, but this
whole theme of הבל הבלים hevel havelim and about like the sense
of loss and what you know the waste and whatever and the
crying. All that is a more appropriate on the way there than
on the way back. רמב"ם Rambam as I remember correctly also says
it's on the way back, but that's important to know that there's
a reading of it on the way there. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues. אמר ליה רבא בר רב חנן לאביי, היכי עבדי?
amar lei Rava bar Rav Chanan le-Abaye, heichi avdi? So
how would you how what did people used to how do they
do this? What would they do for the מעמד ומושב? ma-amad u-moshav?
אמר ליה, כדתניא, אמר רבי יהודה, בראשונה לא היו פוחתים משבעה מעמדות
ומושבות. ki-detanya, amar Rabbi Yehuda, be-rishona lo hayu pochtim mi-shiva ma-amados u-moshavos.
It says in
יהודה *Yehuda*, in the Judea, they used to, they would never do
fewer than seven sittings and standings. במאי כגון *Bamei k'gon*, and here's
what they would say: עמדו יקרים עמדו *Amdu yekarim amodu*, שבו יקרים
שבו *Shivu yekarim shevu*. So, you know, oh honored ones rise up,
honored ones sit down. So that's how they would give directions to
say when are we sitting, when are we standing and moving forward
and so on. It didn't say what they would actually do when
they were sitting and standing, but at least it gives you a
sense of some of the structure. אמרו לו *Amru lo*, so they
said to him, אם כן אף בשבת מותר לעשות כן *im kein
af be-Shabbos mutar la-asos kein*. If that's all you're doing by the
מעמדות ומושבות *ma'amados u-moshavos*, sitting and standing, maybe saying some words, then
you could even do it on שבת *Shabbos*. And why not? Because
you're doing it in the context of burying. Well, so we're going
to have to deal with that. How did you get a burial
to be on שבת *Shabbos*? The גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is going to
say you buried the person right before שבת *Shabbos* and you're coming
back from the grave—from the graveyard and it's already getting dark or
it's already dark. But presumably anyway, the רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda*—the חכמים
*Chachamim* were saying we know you're not allowed to do מעמד ומושב
*ma'amad u-moshav* on שבת *Shabbos*, and the way you explained it, they
say to רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda*, what would be the problem? Now
of course maybe the problem isn't a מלאכה *melacha* on שבת *Shabbos*,
maybe if the sitting and the standing is the wailing and the
mourning and the so on, like that's not appropriate on שבת *Shabbos*.
ניחום אבלים *Nichum aveilim* is actually technically allowed, but this type of
this mourning and so on is not. But anyway, so that's what
they're saying. They're saying like you haven't explained enough what the problem
is about doing it on שבת *Shabbos*
because maybe from him it sounds like they were just sitting and
standing and he didn't say anything else was part of it, right,
which is okay. If all you do is you're sitting and standing
and sitting and standing and just taking your time, you know, in
terms of returning from the בית הקברות *beis hakvaros*, why can't you
do a sitting and standing on שבת *Shabbos* as well? So presumably
there has to be more, there has to be some of this
wailing or whatever. One minute. Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara* says
like this: By the way, as we're going to see, okay. So,
אחותיה דרמי בר פפא *achsei de-Rami bar Papa*, the sister of רמי
בר פפא *Rami bar Papa*, הוי נסיבא ליה לרב אביא *havi nesiva
lei le-Rav Avya*, was married to רב אביא *Rav Avya*. שכיבא *Shchiva*,
when she—she died. עבד לה מעמד ומושב *Avad lah ma'amad u-moshav*, he
did a מעמד *ma'amad* and a מושב *moshav* for her. אמר רב
יוסף *Amar Rav Yosef*, טעה בתרתי *ta ba-tartei*, he made two mistakes
when he did that for her, for his wife. טעה שאין עושין
אלא בקרובים והוא עבד אפילו ברחוקים *ta she-ein osim ela bi-krovim ve-hu
avad afilu bi-rchokim*. First of all, the only people who are supposed
to participate in the מעמד ומושב *ma'amad u-moshav* are the relatives. Again,
the way the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* and others explain it means not
the mourners themselves, you know, I mean they're there, but the point—what
we're pointing about here is the extended family are the participants, not
strangers. And he apparently involved people that were—I mean not strangers, friends
but not family. So apparently he involved friends in this process and
not just family. Number one. Meaning what was the problem? He did
it in the wrong way. He did it right—he arranged it, he
did the arrangements, he did it in the wrong way. He got—he
had—he had non-family members involved. וטעה שאין עושין אלא ביום ראשון והוא
עבד ביום שני *Ve-ta she-ein osim ela be-yom rishon ve-hu avad be-yom
sheini*. And number one, we only do this on the first day,
the day of the burial, which is now explained also why it's
the day of returning. And he apparently did it on like a
second day, you know, after the—after the מת *meis* had been buried
the day before, he said, hey let's do the מעמדות ומושבות *ma'amados
u-moshavos*. So he misunderstood what the context—what the standards of the practice
were. אביי אמר בהא נמי טעה *Abaye amar ba-ha nami ta*, he
made a third mistake. שאין עושין אלא בבית הקברות *she-ein osim ela
be-veis hakvaros*, that all of this is going back to how we've
described what happens. It's done in the context of the actual cemetery.
Here it says in the cemetery itself, but you know, but some—but
presumably it's like near the cemetery. והוא עבד בעיר *Ve-hu avad ba-ir*,
and he waited—and he did it even after everybody had returned to
the city. I mean, once it's on the second day, of course
everybody's back in the town. I guess you could say maybe on
the second day they went out back to the cemetery to do
it, but no. He did it when they were not in the
process of returning. We do it in the process of returning near
the cemetery. He did it on the second day in the town
itself. רבא אמר בהא נמי טעה *Rava amar ba-ha nami ta*, he
made a fourth mistake. שאין עושין אלא במקום שנהגו והתם לא נהגו
*She-ein osim ela be-makom she-nahagu ve-hasam lo nahagu*, which explains why he
got it wrong because it wasn't a standard practice. So he thought
he would like reinstitute the practice but he didn't understand this. Okay,
מתיבי *meisvei*, now the גמרא *Gemara* says one minute. I have a
question. If it's really true that the practice was only on the
day of, it's going to ask the question Michael asked, which is
how could we be discussing doing it on שבת *Shabbos*? Since when
can you bury someone on שבת *Shabbos*? אמרו לו אם כן אף
בשבת מותר לעשות כן *Amru lo im kein af be-Shabbos mutar la-asos
kein*. ואם אמרת בבית הקברות ביום ראשון *Ve-im amart be-veis hakvaros be-yom
rishon*, if you—if it was only done in the cemetery on the
first day, on the day of burial, so the גמרא *Gemara* says
בית הקברות בשבת מאי בעי *be-veis hakvaros be-Shabbos mai ba'ei*? So how
are you—what are you doing in the cemetery on שבת *Shabbos*? What
are you doing burying the body on שבת *Shabbos*? So the גמרא
*Gemara* says no, בעיר הסמוכה לבית הקברות דמטו בין השמשות *be-ir ha-smucha
le-veis hakvaros de-mitu bein ha-shmashos*. No, no, the town was—the cemetery was
very close to the town so they brought the body out. It
says בין השמשות *bein ha-shmashos*, but presumably it has to mean like
right before it sunset, it got dark, and therefore as they were
returning it was already שבת *Shabbos*. They—which by the way, right, explains—reinforces
the idea that it was only on the return, not on the
going, because if it was on the going then you can't explain
how they were doing it on שבת *Shabbos*. So maybe I appreciate
Dave what you said and maybe according to that רש"י *Rashi* they
also did it on the going, but at least anyway here from
the גמרא *Gemara* it's clear that it refers to a case of
return. All right, and therefore they said to רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda*,
if you're just sitting and standing you would be able to do
that if you're returning on שבת *Shabbos* and all you're doing is
sitting and standing you should be able to do it. It must
be there's more, it must be there's wailing and mourning and so
on. Yes, and I've just happened to been wondering over that. Yes.
And before it’s not תוספות, it’s רבינו גרשום. Rabbeinu Gershom. רבינו גרשום
Rabbeinu Gershom yes okay. But before when we had the גרסא Girsa
that דרך הקבר אין לו שיעור derech hakever ein lo shiur and
our גרסא Girsa is ומשום יקרא דשיכבא, umishum yekara deshichva, he has
זבילותא דשיכבא zivluta deshichva and ואיקרא. ve'ikara. He says וצריך להרחיב יותר
שלא יריחו הכל ריח. vetzarich leharchiv yoter shelo yarichu hakol rei'ach.
One more time. He says זבילותא דשיכבא ואיקרא. zivluta deshichva ve'ikara. And
how is it זבילותא? zivluta? בגלל שלא יריחו הכל
ריח. biglal shelo yarichu hakol rei'ach. So I, actually יריחו, yarichu, יריחו,
yarichu, you know. Oh, ריח, rei'ach, יריחו, yarichu, so it’s to the...
to the body, it’s... Oh,
you need more space to allow the so that it wouldn’t... people
wouldn't be so close to it and smell the decomposing body. That’s
interesting. Okay, let’s read the next משנה, Mishnah, let’s start the next
משנה. Mishnah. המוכר מקום לחברו לעשות לו קבר וכן המקבל מחברו לעשות
לו קבר. Hamocher makom lachavero la'asot lo kever vechen hamikabel michavero la'asot
lo kever.
This is similar to the idea, you know, somebody sold somebody a
plot of land because you know the person wanted to build a
house for his son, or you hired a contractor to build a
house for your son. So now, different story. You sold... the guy
sold a plot of land for somebody who wanted to use it
for a... for a grave, you know, for his... for his family.
Okay, or the guy took a contracting job to help make a
grave for somebody’s family. Now, the grave here does not mean just
קבר, kever, but it does not mean just digging a hole in
the ground, or going to see as you could tell if your
eyes wander over to the next page and see all those pretty
pictures. We’re going to be dealing with the... with the ways in
which that they had, you know, these niches into... into caves, which
were family grave sites. Now, apparently that was only for the wealthy.
Apparently the normal person was buried in the ground even in a
time of the גמרא, at least that’s what my research last night
on the web showed.
But you know, but they have found actually, you know, many of
these types of... of burial caves in Israel, but again, they were,
you know, they were very fancily done and you know, there’s... you
know, even with all that they found, obviously it’s a tiny percentage
of the amount of people who have died. You know, so these...
anyway, the assumption is based I think on the grandeur of them
or whatever, that this was only done for the wealthy. So this
is presumably the context of the משנה, Mishnah, that somebody is selling
a plot of... a cave to be used for this purpose or
has contracted to actually construct a cave for this, it was not
just... obviously it might have started with a natural cave, but if
you look at any of these pictures, you know, they have these
very grand like... edifices, or what do they call them? What are
the front things called?
Facades, right, on them, you know, this whole big entranceways with columns
and the whole type of thing. Okay, but anyway, we’re not dealing
with that. We’re just dealing with the space that’s needed for this.
So המוכר מקום לחברו לעשות לו קבר וכן המקבל מחברו לעשות לו
קבר Hamocher makom lachavero la'asot lo kever vechen hamikabel michavero la'asot lo
kever עושה תוכו של מערה ארבע אמות על שש ופותח לתוכה שמונה
כוכים שלוש מכאן ושלוש מכאן ושניים מכנגדן. oseh tocho shel me'arah arba
amot al shesh upoteach letocha shemonah kuchin shalosh mikan veshalosh mikan ushnayim
mikinegedan. Okay,
so basically for a standard cave, it would be, what does it
say? ארבע אמות על שש, arba amot al shesh, six by four,
and you would have... so this would be the cave. Here the
person... you would walk in. Okay, so you’d have three... three niches
here, three niches here, and two niches here, which would be a
total of eight. Okay, so the רשב"ם says that the diameter, you’d
allow it to be a half אמה amah here. Each niche would
be an אמה. amah. Okay, and there’d be... so there’d be a
half between them.
Okay, so in that case, that’s one, two, three אמות. amot. Two
halves is... wait, did I do that right? No, I’m sorry. It’d
be one and a half... one between them. Excuse me. One between
them and a half at the edges. Okay, so one, two, three
אמות amot for the three niches. Two for the spaces between them
is five and then six. And then similarly here, okay? One, two,
a third between them and two halves at the edge. Okay, so
that’s how you’d have the niches. Okay, so... עושה oseh so... ופותח
לתוכה שמונה כוכים שלוש מכאן ושלוש מכאן ושניים מכנגדן upoteach letocha shemonah
kuchin shalosh mikan veshalosh mikan ushnayim mikinegedan וכוכים אורכן ארבע אמות, vekuchin
orchan arba amot, now these כוכים kuchin themselves, the
niches, they would be four אמות amot length. Okay, ארבע אמות ורומן
שבעה, arba amot veruman shivah,
they would be seven טפחים tefachim high. Okay, so which is basically
an אמה amah and a sixth high. ורומן שבעה ורחבן שישה veruman
shivah verachban shishah
and their width, as we just said, would be six טפחים, tefachim,
which would be one אמה. amah. Now I want to stop here...
be whole אמה amah is... no an אמה amah is six טפחים.
tefachim. Okay, I just want to stop here for a second because
this is basically the size of a body. So now, the first
thing it says is ארבע אמות. arba amot. ארבע אמות Arba amot
is six feet, okay? And the average height, you know, in the
ancient world was about... was a little bit shorter, although I heard
there’s some debate how much variation there really was. But anyway, but
the average height was about five feet seven inches or something like
that, five feet six inches. Jews I think have... I don’t know
if they’ve always been smaller, but anyway, probably... Mediterranean people have always
been a little smaller. So that's presumably considered enough, six feet. Okay,
that's the four אמות. amot. The seven טפחים tefachim is the height
of the body, right? Or the width of the body, right? So
that's like a little bit more than an אמה, amah, that makes
sense. I think that the width of a body is not more
than like a foot and a half. What I don't really understand
is is is this, that this is only one אמה, amah, the
sort of what you need to get the body across. Right? That's
a foot and a half. I think the average shoulder width, right?
I mean you're widest at the shoulders, right? Is, it's gotta be
more than like 18 inches, isn't it? Or just about 18 inches?
No?
So it's tall, it's six feet tall. Six? Oh, meaning, yeah. It's
three dimensions. Right, there need to be three dimensions. I'll erase this
for a minute. If you think about here. Right,
there you go, there's the coffin, okay? There's the body. Okay? So
anyway, so this thing he is four אמות. amot. I'm going to
do it in six feet. Six feet long, okay? A seven טפחים
tefachim high, which is basically 21 inches high, right? And then but
the thing is it's only six טפחים, tefachim, it's only 18 inches
wide. So I don't get exactly how 18 inches wide is supposed
to what?
Diagonally? Maybe even on the side.
Oh, maybe.
Yeah.
Yeah. At the yoga class. So I don't know if any of
your Artscrolls or Soncinos like deal with that question. Now, I do
want to say, we'll pick up with this though. I do want
to say that, you know, and I'm trying to figure this out,
what they would do is they'd let the body decompose, and then
they would take the bones and they'd move the bones to another
place, which would allow for more compact storage. But it sounded to
me from this description, I have to research it more, that we
were talking about before it had decomposed, while it was still in
its full size. So, yeah, right. And did they discuss how exactly
the width is supposed to only be an אמה amah wide? From
what I researched last year, yeah, but that they would be shelves
that they would put them on
until they decomposed. And then they'd put them in the niches. Right,
so that's what I was thinking. If actually right, and that's actually
what I was able to find as well. So if actually that's
what you're doing, then, you know, now when they would put them
in the niches, would they just sort of like, you know, pack
up the bones? Or would they be in their skeletal shape? But
if they were in their skeletal shape, right, then even so if
all you have is bones and not flesh, you could imagine how
that could how you could manage with just that width. But I
that's I think a core question. Were they put in in a
skeletal form? Why would they do that? I mean it's just I
don't think they do. They don't have materials to hold it together.
Right. Well, unless you actually had a plank and you would just
but I don't think they do. That's what I didn't understand. So
if right, so if once it turns to bones you pack them
in, you don't need this big of a space. And if we're
talking about the actual body then I still don't exactly get how
18 inches across is going to be enough. And then you can
use the across. Yeah. All right, anyway, to be continued. I mean,
yeah.